<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://der41.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://der41.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-09T02:44:21+00:00</updated><id>https://der41.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Real Estate Sector in China</title><link href="https://der41.github.io/blog/2023/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Estate Sector in China"/><published>2023-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://der41.github.io/blog/2023/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://der41.github.io/blog/2023/distill/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="context">Context</h2> <p>The real estate sector represents a significant portion of China’s economy. <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/rogoff/publications/peak-china-housing">Rogoff and Yang (2021)</a> estimate that, prior to the sector’s crisis, its contribution to the economy—including related industries—accounted for approximately 30% of GDP. This figure is well above the median of 16% of GDP for developed countries analyzed in their study. The sector’s boom was driven by increasing demand for urbanization, economic growth, and government policies favoring investment over the past decade.</p> <p>In China, properties account for more than 50% of household wealth (<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1043951X21000730">Li and Zhang, 2021</a>)<d-footnote> In the study by Li and Zhang, real estate as household wealth in European countries reaches a maximum of 30%, while in the United Kingdom, the figure is slightly above 10%.</d-footnote>, and land sales contribute roughly 30% of local government revenues (<a href="https://www.piie.com/publications/working-papers/why-chinas-housing-policies-have-failed">Huang, 2023</a>). Given China’s global economic significance, and its particular importance for Chile, monitoring the state of its real estate market is of special interest. This blog analyzes the causes of the current crisis and its outlook.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="imbalances">Imbalances</h2> <p>China’s real estate market has been undergoing a severe contraction since 2021. Over the past two years, housing sales and new housing starts have plummeted by 30% and 60%, respectively (Figure 1). At the same time, housing prices have fallen by around 10% in some cities. This deterioration is attributed to two structural problems:</p> <ol> <li>An oversupply of housing, particularly in lower-income cities;</li> <li>Financial vulnerabilities accumulated by real estate developers during the expansion years.</li> </ol> <div class="l-page" style="display: flex; justify-content: center; align-items: center; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;"> <iframe frameborder="0" sandbox="allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation" scrolling="no" src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/15568110/embed?auto=1" style="box-sizing:border-box; width:700px; height:560px; object-fit: cover; object-position: top;" title="Interactive or visual content"> </iframe> </div> <p>Several factors explain the oversupply in China’s housing market. On one hand, for many years, there was a high pace of construction, encouraged by government policies as part of its growth strategy. On the other hand, structural factors have weakened demand and are expected to continue doing so in the future. Specifically, population aging and slowing migration flows have reduced demand and are likely to persist in the coming years (<a href="https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/WP/Issues/2022/09/29/A-Tale-of-Tier-3-Cities-524064">Rogoff and Yang, 2022</a>). Additionally, demographic growth is expected to turn negative, homeownership rates are high (90%), and the average age of housing stock is relatively low.</p> <p>In recent years, demand has also been impacted by the pandemic and the real estate market crisis, which has further dampened demand due to doubts about the financial health of developers and declining housing prices.</p> <p>The second structural problem is the financial fragility accumulated by real estate developers. Over the past 20 years, developers accrued debt (from households, banks, and others) at a faster rate than the growth of their assets, leading to an increase in the liabilities-to-assets ratio from about 70% to 80% (Figure 2). This debt increase was driven by government policies favoring the sector and by the developers’ business model.</p> <div class="l-page" style="display: flex; justify-content: center; align-items: center; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;"> <iframe frameborder="0" sandbox="allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation" scrolling="no" src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/15567856/embed?auto=1" style="box-sizing:border-box; width:700px; height:560px; object-fit: cover; object-position: top;" title="Interactive or visual content"> </iframe> </div> <p>This model relies on rapid project turnover, heavy dependence on pre-sales, and significant leverage. A typical cycle involves a developer obtaining pre-sale funds for a housing unit and securing loans from various financial intermediaries to purchase land from local governments. The developer then begins construction, selling unfinished homes years before completion to buyers who start paying mortgages before the houses are fully built. One key vulnerability of this business model is the potential for severe liquidity pressures if any steps in this cycle fail (<a href="https://www.piie.com/publications/working-papers/why-chinas-housing-policies-have-failed">Huang, 2023</a>).</p> <p>These issues significantly affected the sector’s activity after the introduction of various government policies aimed at controlling the debt levels of real estate developers. In particular, the “three red lines” policy introduced by the Chinese government in August 2020 set limits on three financial ratios that developers must meet in order to access new credit. Following this policy, only three developers met all the criteria, while the rest failed to meet at least one. Notably, Evergrande, Sunac, and Greenland failed to meet all three. With the contraction of the sector and accumulated vulnerabilities, many companies have experienced significant liquidity and/or solvency problems in recent years, including Evergrande and Country Garden<d-footnote>An example of this is the situation with Evergrande (IEF, second half of 2021) and Country Garden (La Tercera, 2023). </d-footnote>. As a result, these companies have seen significant drops in their valuations, which have not yet recovered (Figure 3).</p> <div class="l-page" style="display: flex; justify-content: center; align-items: center; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;"> <iframe frameborder="0" sandbox="allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation" scrolling="no" src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/15568021/embed?auto=1" style="box-sizing:border-box; width:700px; height:560px; object-fit: cover; object-position: top;" title="Interactive or visual content"> </iframe> </div> <p>Since then, the authorities have implemented various measures to support the sector, though these have had limited effects. Among these measures, packages to restore financing channels for developers and relaxations of restrictions on home purchases for families stand out. As of September this year, the effects have been modest, in a context where consumer confidence remains at historically low levels, housing prices continue to fall, and doubts persist about the financial health of developers. Recently, an expansion of the fiscal deficit by 0.8% of GDP was announced to address the slowdown. This stimulus, to be implemented immediately, could provide some relief (likely temporary) to the sector.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="outlook">Outlook</h2> <p>The sector’s and China’s economic outlook will depend on how the government’s response evolves. If the current situation persists, with relatively limited stimulus efforts, the sector is likely to face a prolonged adjustment, resulting in slow economic growth compared to historical trends. However, if more fiscal stimulus is implemented to reactivate activity and boost confidence, as recently announced, economic activity will likely recover more strongly in the short term but will increase the risk associated with the country’s elevated sovereign debt levels. A bailout for struggling companies also carries the risk of increasing sovereign debt and potential moral hazard. Lastly, a restructuring of developers’ debt will affect the financial situation of households and banks.</p> <p>Despite the challenges, China’s situation has two key mitigating factors compared to past crises in other economies. On one hand, the country has accumulated current account surpluses over the last few decades, which limits the possibility of a sudden stop due to a loss of confidence in the country. Additionally, despite the high exposure of the banking sector to the real estate market, the greater prevalence of state ownership in banks reduces the likelihood of a banking crisis in this context.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ul> <li>Rogoff, Kenneth, and Yuanchen Yang. 2021. “Has China’s Housing Production Peaked?” China and the World Economy 21 (1): 1-31.</li> <li>Cheng Li, Ying Zhang. 2021. “How does housing wealth affect household consumption? Evidence from macro-data with special implications for China”, China Economic Review 69.</li> <li>Huang Tianlei. 2023 “Why China’s housing policies have failed” PIIE Working Paper 23-6.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Lucas Bertinatto</name></author><category term="Economy"/><category term="China"/><category term="Real-Estate"/><category term="Analytics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A translation of the original blog written at the Central Bank of Chile]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Processing Incoming Data into Actionable Reports</title><link href="https://der41.github.io/blog/2021/pagerank/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Processing Incoming Data into Actionable Reports"/><published>2021-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://der41.github.io/blog/2021/pagerank</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://der41.github.io/blog/2021/pagerank/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="context">Context:</h2> <h3 id="organizing-dynamic-data">Organizing Dynamic Data</h3> <p>Have you ever dealt with dynamic data that changes daily, monthly, or quarterly? Each day can bring a completely new dataset, and keeping track of it all can feel overwhelming—especially when you need to plan your activities and timeline based on incoming information.</p> <p>Take the international economy, for example. Before the business day begins, you might already have over 16 new global indicators to process. Some will exceed market forecasts, while others fall short. This pattern repeats daily, with different indicators being released every hour.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/economic_calendar-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/economic_calendar-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/economic_calendar-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/economic_calendar.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="pagerank">PageRank</h2> <h3 id="how-can-we-organize-this-chaos">How Can We Organize This Chaos?</h3> <p>The simplest inspiration comes from the PageRank algorithm, originally developed by Google to rank web pages. While Google has since evolved its ranking methods, the foundational concept remains powerful.</p> <p>In a nutshell, PageRank assigns a score of importance to each page, based on the principle that a page becomes more important if other important pages link to it. It’s a recursive system: the importance of a page is determined by the importance of the pages linking to it.As Eric Roberts from Stanford describes, you can imagine a random surfer clicking through links on the web. The PageRank of any given page is the probability that the surfer will land on it. Pages with more incoming links from important sources are more likely to attract the surfer, and thus rank higher in search results. You can find a link to his slides <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/class/cs54n/handouts/24-GooglePageRankAlgorithm.pdf">here</a>.</p> <p>This same logic can be applied to dynamic data. While PageRank used hyperlinks as the core measure for cataloging the early internet, we can adapt its principles to organize economic indicators—leveraging domain knowledge about the data to create a meaningful ranking system.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="application">Application</h2> <h3 id="applying-pagerank-principles-to-economic-data">Applying PageRank Principles to Economic Data</h3> <p>To make sense of chaotic economic data, we need to answer some key questions about the information:</p> <ol> <li>Do we know the frequency of the data release?</li> <li>How valuable is this information each time it’s updated?</li> <li>Are there other characteristics that help predict its relevance and usage?</li> <li>Can we generate metrics that improve our summaries of incoming data?</li> </ol> <p>Answering these questions with confidence allows us to rank the data effectively. This, in turn, enables more efficient querying and retrieval of relevant information, whether it’s data that’s about to be released or historical data for comparison.</p> <p>Let’s use an example. Below is a lookup table that synthesizes the importance of different economic indicators for workflow planning.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Country</th> <th>Data</th> <th>Coming Up Next Week</th> <th>Importance for Workflow</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>USA</td> <td>Employment</td> <td>Yes (1)</td> <td>Very High (5)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>USA</td> <td>Factory Orders</td> <td>Yes (1)</td> <td>Medium (3)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>USA</td> <td>Consumer Confidence</td> <td>No (0)</td> <td>High (4)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>EU</td> <td>Consumer Confidence</td> <td>Yes (1)</td> <td>High (4)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>GER</td> <td>Factory Orders</td> <td>Yes (1)</td> <td>Low (1)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>CHN</td> <td>Aggregate Social Finance</td> <td>No (0)</td> <td>Very High (5)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>In this table:</p> <p>“Coming Up Next Week” is a binary indicator of whether the data will be released soon. “Importance for Workflow” reflects how critical the information is for decision-making. By combining these metrics, we calculate a final score (e.g., by multiplying the two values) to prioritize incoming data.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="python-example">Python Example</h2> <h3 id="from-manual-tracking-to-automation">From Manual Tracking to Automation</h3> <p>Here’s how Python can be used to streamline this process. First, create a DataFrame with your lookup table and another DataFrame holding the forecast, expected, and previous values of the data. Then, merge these tables, calculate the scores, and sort the data to highlight the most critical updates.</p> <div class="jupyter-notebook" style="position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;"> <div class="jupyter-notebook-iframe-container"> <iframe src="/assets/jupyter/pagerank.ipynb.html" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; border-style: none;" width="100%" height="100%" onload="this.parentElement.style.paddingBottom = (this.contentWindow.document.documentElement.scrollHeight + 10) + 'px'"></iframe> </div> </div> <p>This process scales seamlessly. While the example only involves six data entries, the same logic applies to organizing thousands of entries weekly. By automating with lookup tables and scripts, you can shift your focus from manual tracking to strategic analysis.</p> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <h3 id="a-smarter-way-to-manage-dynamic-data">A Smarter Way to Manage Dynamic Data</h3> <p>By borrowing ideas from PageRank and leveraging domain knowledge, you can transform chaotic streams of key indicators into a structured, actionable workflow. Automation ensures that even large volumes of data remain manageable, letting you focus on decision-making instead of data wrangling.</p> <p>So next time you’re buried in dynamic data, think about how you can rank and organize it—because smarter tools will translate into smarter decisions.</p>]]></content><author><name>Diego Rodriguez</name></author><category term="Dashboard"/><category term="Analytics"/><category term="Automation"/><category term="AI"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Applying a PageRank principle to unknown information]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Effortless Real-Time Data Monitoring</title><link href="https://der41.github.io/blog/2020/iframes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effortless Real-Time Data Monitoring"/><published>2020-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://der41.github.io/blog/2020/iframes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://der41.github.io/blog/2020/iframes/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="context">Context:</h2> <h3 id="leveraging-embedded-tools-for-real-time-data">Leveraging Embedded Tools for Real-Time Data</h3> <p>Have you ever needed to track a subject, but simply didn’t have the time to constantly update and check all the necessary information? I faced a similar challenge a few months ago.</p> <p>We were tasked with monitoring the development of the Covid-19 pandemic worldwide on a daily basis. However, we lacked the tools to access and process the information with the level of detail and frequency we needed, while also keeping track of the usual economic indicators we were monitoring.</p> <p>This is where the internet can be a game-changer. When you find the right source, in the right place, it becomes incredibly easy to consolidate information and keep your audience informed about current developments without unnecessary effort.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="owid">OWID</h2> <h3 id="our-world-in-data-a-lifesaver-for-real-time-tracking-of-covid-19">Our World in Data: A Lifesaver for Real-Time Tracking of Covid-19</h3> <p>OurWorldinData (OWID) did an outstanding job of tracking the pandemic in real-time. Thanks to them, we were able to embed their information directly into our trackers, allowing us to see what’s happening across the world without spending any extra time on the tedious process of Extracting, Transforming, and Loading (ETL) an increasing variety of data. For example, the graph below shows the Oxford Stringency Index across various countries, and we’re not loading any data ourselves. We’re simply using an embedded iframe from OWID’s website.</p> <div class="l-page" style="display: flex; justify-content: center; align-items: center; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;"> <iframe src="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/covid?country=USA~ITA~CAN~DEU~GBR~FRA&amp;hideControls=true&amp;Metric=Stringency+index&amp;Interval=7-day+rolling+average&amp;Relative+to+population=true&amp;tab=chart" loading="lazy" style="width: 68%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;" allow="web-share; clipboard-write"> </iframe> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="iframes">iFrames</h2> <h3 id="what-is-it-and-how-does-it-work">What Is It and How Does It Work?</h3> <p>In essence, an iframe (short for “inline frame”) allows you to embed another HTML document within your current web page, creating a “page within a page.” This feature is commonly used to display content such as videos, maps, or forms from another website without redirecting your audience elsewhere. In our case, we embedded a specific view from <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/metrics-explained-covid19-stringency-index">OWID</a> website—just one of many useful resources available in real-time.</p> <p>Here is a look to the underlying iframe object presented above:</p> <div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;div</span>
  <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"l-page"</span>
  <span class="na">style=</span><span class="s">"display: flex; justify-content: center; 
align-items: center; margin: 20px 0; overflow: hidden;"</span>
<span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;iframe</span>
    <span class="na">src=</span><span class="s">"https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/covid?country=USA~ITA~CAN~DEU~GBR~FRA&amp;hideControls=true&amp;Metric=Stringency+index&amp;Interval=7-day+rolling+average&amp;Relative+to+population=true&amp;tab=chart"</span>
    <span class="na">loading=</span><span class="s">"lazy"</span>
    <span class="na">style=</span><span class="s">"width: 68%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;"</span>
    <span class="na">allow=</span><span class="s">"web-share; clipboard-write"</span>
  <span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/iframe&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <hr/> <h2 id="minimal-dashboards">Minimal Dashboards</h2> <h3 id="with-minimal-effort">With Minimal Effort</h3> <p>These kinds of tools are incredibly helpful for organizing information in a dashboard format. By doing so, you can get a quick overview of developments on a given topic, saving time and effort. That’s exactly how we kept track of the pandemic without investing unnecessary resources into data extraction or management. The image below illustrates how we organized and tracked the data effectively back then.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Iframe_dashboard-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Iframe_dashboard-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Iframe_dashboard-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Iframe_dashboard.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>In summary, this approach is invaluable when your primary goal is staying informed and thinking strategically about the next steps in your analysis. By leveraging external resources like OWID and embedding them into dashboards, we were able to gain significant insights with minimal effort, allowing us to focus on what truly matters without getting bogged down by complex data workflows.</p>]]></content><author><name>Diego Rodriguez</name></author><category term="Dashboard"/><category term="Analytics"/><category term="Automation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you require information without ETL]]></summary></entry></feed>